Elisha Kent Kane Papers 1810-1973 1843-1857 Mss.B.K132
American Philosophical Society
- Series I. Correspondence, 1810-1953 (bulk: 1843-1857); 5.5 linear feet
  - 1856 August 21, 1 item; Royal Geographical Society (Great Britain) (Box 10)
  - 1851 November 20, 1 item; Rufner, S. (Box 10)
  - 1851 October 14, 1 item; Rupal, S. (Box 10)
  - 1852-1853, 8 items; Russell, G. R. (Box 10)
  - 1852 October 25, 1 item; Salem Charitable Mechanic Association (Box 10)
  - 1804 December 20, 1 item; Sanderson, James (Box 10)
  - 1852 November 5, 1 item; Sargeant, L. P. (Box 10)
  - 1852 October 9, 1 item; Sartain, John (Box 10)
  - Indenture, 1833 April 17; 1 item; Say, Benjamin (Box 10)
  - Folder 1. 1852, 15 items; Schott, Charles A. (Box 10)
  - Folder 2. 1953, n.d., 7 items; Schott, Charles A. (Box 10)
  - 1853 March 18, 1 item; Schweinitz, Bernard de (Box 10)
  - 1848 February 13, 1 item; Scott, Winfield (Box 10)
  - n.d., 1 item; Seaman, Mr. (Box 10)
  - 1853 February 6, 1 item; Seaver, Benjamin (Box 10)
  - 1845-1853, 2 items; Selden, Henry (Box 10)
  - 1853 February 16, 1 item; Shaw, R. G. (Box 10)
  - 1843 July 4, 1 item; Shields, Bessie Kane (Box 10)
  - 1856 October 7, 1 item; Shields, C. W. (Box 10)
  - 1854 April 11, 1 item; Sickles, D. E. (Box 10)
  - 1849-n.d., 4 items; Sinclair, Arthur (Box 10)
  - 1850-1852, 2 items; Sinclair, W. M. (Box 10)
  - n.d., 1 item; Smith, F. M. (Box 10)
  - 1847, n.d., 2 items; Smith, Henry H. (Box 10)
  - 1848 May 17, 1 item; Smith, John B. (Box 10)
  - 1852-1853, Smith, J. P. (Box 10)
  - 1851-1856, 10 items; Smith, William P. (Box 10)
  - 1846 November, 1 item; Smoot, Joseph R. (Box 10)
  - 1846 December 31, 1 item; Smoots, Capt. (Box 10)
  - 1845 August 14, n.d., 2 items; Snider, Jacob, Jr. (Box 10)
  - 1853 May 13, 1 item; Sonntag, August (Box 10)
  - n.d., 1 item; Souza, Ant (Box 10)
  - 1849-1852, 2 items; Sprague, E. R. (Box 10)
  - 1853 March 10, 1 item; Stalecrath (?), George Henry (Box 10)
  - 1853 March 16, 1 item; Stanley, C. H. (Box 10)
  - 1853 March 14, 1 item; Stevens, William Bacon (Box 10)
  - 1847 April 26, 1 item; Stewart, Charles (Box 10)
  - 1845 April 9, 1 item; Stewart, George W. (Box 10)
  - 1856 October 10, 1 item; Stewart, Joseph J. (Box 10)
  - 1853-n.d., 2 items; Stimpson, William (Box 10)
  - 1856 October 1, 1 item; Stone, Henry (Box 10)
  - 1852 October 26, 1 item; Streeter, L. (Box 10)
  - 1852 January 23, 1 item; Strickland, [Nimrod?] (Box 10)
  - 1844 June 26, 1 item; Sturgis, Russell (Box 10)
  - Settlement, 1844 September 1; 1 item; Sullivan, M. G. (Box 10)
  - 1853 January 22, 1 item; Sutton, William (Box 10)
  - 1851 October 20, 1 item; Symmes, John C. (Box 10)
  - n.d., 1 item; Tagore, Dwarkanoth (Box 11)
  - 1852-1853, 5 items; Tasker, Lyman H. (Box 11)
  - n.d., 1 item; Taylor, G. (Box 11)
  - 1846, 1 item; Taylor, John N. (Box 11)
  - n.d., 1 item; Taylor, Lucy P. (Box 11)
  - 1845-1847, 3 items; Thomas, Ann G. (Box 11)
  - 1853 February 9, 1 item; Thomas, H. G. (Box 11)
  - 1847-1856, 4 items; Thomas, John A. (Box 11)
  - 1852 August 27, 1 item; Thomas, Mary L. (Box 11)
  - 1852, 2 items; Thornton, D. M. (Box 11)
  - 1849-1852, 3 items; Thornton, M. J. (Box 11)
  - 1852-1853, 3 items; Tillinghast, James (Box 11)
  - 1848 January 3, 3 items; Torrejon, Anatt. (Box 11)
  - 1852 October 25, 1 item; Tucker, J. T. (Box 11)
  - 1846-1847, 5 items; Tuckerman, J. Francis (Box 11)
  - 1853 March 28, 1 item; Tufts, Samuel, Jr. (Box 11)
  - Jalapa, Mexico, 1847; 1 item; U.S. Army Hospital Report (Box 11)
  - Proceedings of a General Court Marshal, 1846; 1 item; U.S. Navy (Box 11)
  - 1829-1853, 10 items; U.S. Secretary of the Navy (Box 11)
  - 1848 November 20, 1 item; U.S. Secretary of War (Box 11)
  - 1848-1852, 5 items; U.S. Treasury Dept. (Box 11)
  - 1846-1847, 2 items; VanWyck, C. C. (Box 11)
  - 1845 July 11, 1 item; Vaughan, Petty (Box 11)
  - 1849 April 9, 1 item; Vezzana, General (Box 11)
  - 1857 January 1, 1 item; Victor, O. I. (Box 11)
  - 1856 October 26, 1 item; Vinton, Francis (Box 11)
  - 1850, 5 items; Vreeland, Benjamin (Box 11)
    Two letters from Kane to Vreeland have name misspelled as Freeland: June 28-30 and July 5
  - 1855 December 27, 1 item; Waddell, W. C. (Box 11)
  - 1847, 2 items; Waln, William Jr. (Box 11)
  - 1856-1857, 2 items; Ward, A. H. (Box 11)
  - 1846-1850, n.d., 2 folders; Weaver, William H. (Box 11)
    - Folder 1, 1846-1848; 18 items (Box 11)
    - Folder 2, 1849-1850, n.d.; 15 items (Box 11)
  - 1842 November 23, 1 item; Webster, D. (Box 11)
  - 1852-1853, n.d., 6 items; Webster, Fletcher (Box 11)
  - 1853 January 29, 1 item; Welles, F. N. (Box 11)
  - n.d., 1 item; Wells, Charles H. (Box 11)
  - 1852 February 18, 1 item; Wells, H. T. (Box 11)
  - 1851-1852, 3 items; Wells, S. R. (Box 11)
  - 1852, 2 items; Welsh, Henry (Box 11)
  - 1852 February 3, 1 item; Welsh, W. H. (Box 11)
  - 1852 November 5, 1 item; Westall, John (Box 11)
  - 1848 November, 3 items; Wetherill, Samuel (Box 11)
  - 1848 May 4, 2 items; Wetmore and Co. (Box 11)
  - n.d, 1 item; Wharton, Mr. (Box 11)
  - 1857 February 18, 1 item; Wharton, William H. (Box 11)
  - 1856 July 7, 1 item; Wheaton, Charles (Box 11)
  - 1852 November 5, 1 item; Whitting, John G. (Box 11)
  - 1842, 1 item; Whydah Slave Trade (Box 11)
  - 1852, 2 items; Williams, Edwin (Box 11)
  - 1849 January 30, 1 item; Williams, Israel L. (Box 11)
  - 1852 February 26, 1 item; Williamson, Robert (Box 11)
  - 1856 October 5, 1 item; Willis, Nathaniel P. (Box 11)
  - 1853 January 12, 1 item; Wilson, John Wall (Box 11)
  - n.d., 1 items; Wilson, R. P. (Box 11)
  - 1853 January 13, 1 item; Wise, John (Box 11)
  - 1856 September 10, 1 item; Wivild, N. (Box 11)
  - n.d., 1 item; Wood, C. M. (Box 11)
  - n.d., 1 item; Wood, H. N. (Box 11)
  - 1852-n.d., 2 items; Wood, J. Walter (Box 11)
  - 1848, n.d., 2 items; Wood, William W. (Box 11)
  - n.d., 1 item; Wood, Mr. (Box 11)
  - 1853 January 3, 1 item; Wright, Charles W. (Box 11)
  - 1852 October 22, 1 item; Wright, Edwin (Box 11)
  - 1852 October 21, 1 item; W.M.C.A. (Box 11)
  - n.d., 1 item; Young, Dr. (Macao) (Box 11)
  - 1840 September 29, 1 item; Zucker, William (Box 11)
  - 1845-1857, n.d., 2 folders; Unidentified correspondents (Box 11)
    - Folder 1, 1845-1857; 6 items (Box 11)
    - Folder 2, n.d.; 11 items (Box 11)
- Series II. Financial Records, 1831-1861; 0.25 linear feet
  Bills, receipts and accounts relating to Elisha Kent Kane's personal finances. The records are arranged chronologically.
  - Bills and receipts, 1831-1861, n.d.; 8 folders; Kane, Elisha Kent, 1820-1857
    - Folder 1, 1831-1845
    - Folder 2, 1846-1847
    - Folder 3, 1848-1849
    - Folder 4, 1850-1851
    - Folder 5, 1852
    - Folder 6, 1853-1855
    - Folder 7, 1856-1861
    - Folder 8, n.d.
- Series III. George W. Corner, Notes on Elisha Kent Kane, 1854-1973; 0.25 linear feet
  Notes and miscellaneous materials assembled by George W. Corner while writing his biography of Elisha Kent Kane. The series includes copies of letters and documents relating to Kane and his expeditions held in other libraries, as well as some of Corner's notes and drafts of writings on Kane.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition note
  Gift of Mrs. E. Paul DuPont, Aug. 13, 1973 (accn. 1973-1615ms).
  - Elisha Kent Kane Medical History (drafts), 1965; 3 folders
    Folder 1 Includes Robert L. Levy, "Notes on the Case of Elisha Kent Kane. MD"
  - "The Facts Relating to the Separation of the Ship's Company of the Brig Advance In the Fall of 1854", n.d.; TMs Cy, 16p.; Goodfellow, Henry.
  - Kane, Elisha Kent. Annotated bibliography, n.d.; 2 folders
  - Correspondence, 1843, n.d.; 4 folders; Kane, Elisha Kent, 1820-1857
    - Folders 1-3, n.d.
    - Folder 4, 1843
      Includes photocopies of originals held by the National Archives, Naval Records
  - Letter to Mary, 1853 April 11; Photocopy, 1p.; Kane, Elisha Kent, 1820-1857
  - Financial accounts, 1853; Photocopies, 24p.; Kane, Elisha Kent, 1820-1857
    Originals at Smithsonian Institution
  - Kane Family Genealogical notes, 1969; 4p.
  - Miscellaneous correspondence relating to Kane biography, 1966-1973
  - Miscellaneous notes, 1965-1969
  - Miscellaneous notes on collections of Kane Papers, 1965-1966
  - Miscellaneous printed materials, 1857-1897; 1960-1967; 2 folders
    - Folder 1, 1857-1897; Photocopies, 4 items
      Includes biographical sketches of Kane and Memoir of Dwarkanath Tagore.
    - Folder 2, 1960-1967; Reprints, 3 items
      Includes A.F.C. Wallace, "An interdisciplinary approach to mental disorder among the Polar Eskimos of Northwest Greenland".
  - History of Ships Named Kane, 1969; 10p.; U.S. Navy. Naval History Division
- Series IV. Bound Volumes, 1835-1860; 1.5 linear feet
  A miscellaneous assemblage of bound volumes of notes, ranging from notes Kane kept as a student at the University of Virginia and University of Pennsylvania, to medical records kept at Blockley Hospital and after, and notebooks and a sketchbook relating to both of his arctic expeditions. Of particular interest are notes on Henry Darwin Rogers' class in mineralogy at the University of Pennsylvania, notes on medical courses taught by Samuel Jackson, and two volumes containing Kane's notes on female patients at Blockley, 1840-1841.
  - Notebook of polar exploration, 1851; Kane, Elisha Kent, 1820-1857 (Volume 1)
  - Medical notebooks, ca.1841-1842; 10 vols; Kane, Elisha Kent, 1820-1857 (Volume 2)
  - Notes on a Trip into North Carolina, 1850; Kane, Elisha Kent, 1820-1857 (Volume 3)
    Some illustrations.
  - Journal of a Trip into the Philippines, ca.1844; Kane, Elisha Kent, 1820-1857 (Volume 4)
  - Journal of a Trip in Africa, 1846; Kane, Elisha Kent, 1820-1857 (Volume 5)
  - Notebook on Asia Minor, n.d.; Kane, Elisha Kent, 1820-1857 (Volume 6)
  - Journal of a Trip in Egypt, ca.1845; Kane, Elisha Kent, 1820-1857 (Volume 7)
  - Sketchbook from Egypt, ca.1845; Kane, Elisha Kent, 1820-1857 (Volume 7a)
  - Journal pertaining to Mexico, 1848; Kane, Elisha Kent, 1820-1857 (Volume 8)
  - Log of the Tilt, June 29-July 16, 1848; Kane, Elisha Kent, 1820-1857 (Volume 9)
  - Arctic exploration letterbook (Private), ca.1850-1851; Kane, Elisha Kent, 1820-1857 (Volume 10)
    Contains many sketches.
    - Inuit kayaking, ca. 1850-1851
    - Inuit kayaking, ca. 1850-1851
  - Notebook of specimens located in the Arctic, ca.1850-1851; Kane, Elisha Kent, 1820-1857 (Volume 11)
  - Logbook, 1850; Kane, Elisha Kent, 1820-1857 (Volume 12)
  - Meteorological Journal, 1850-1851; Kane, Elisha Kent, 1820-1857 (Volume 13)
  - Examination book, University of Virginia, ca.1836; Kane, Elisha Kent, 1820-1857 (Volume 14)
    Contains some sketches.
  - Notes on Geology and Mineralogy, 1839; Kane, Elisha Kent, 1820-1857 (Volume 15)
    Taken in Prof. Rogers' class.
  - Medical lecture notes, University of Pennsylvania, ca.1838-1839; Kane, Elisha Kent, 1820-1857 (Volume 16)
  - Geometry notebook, n.d.; Kane, Elisha Kent, 1820-1857 (Volume 17)
  - Language of algebra, literal quantities, 1835; Kane, Elisha Kent, 1820-1857 (Volume 18)
    "Written with Uncle [Robert M.] Patterson."
  - Memoranda and notes relative to engineering, University of Virginia, ca.1838; Kane, Elisha Kent, 1820-1857 (Volume 19)
  - Medical notebook, Blockley Hospital, 1841; Kane, Elisha Kent, 1820-1857 (Volume 20)
  - Observations on Kiesteine (obstetrics, pregnant women), Blockley Hospital, ca.1841; Kane, Elisha Kent, 1820-1857 (Volume 21)
  - Kyestine, ca.1841; Kane, Elisha Kent, 1820-1857 (Volume 22)
  - Commonplace book, n.d.; Kane, Elisha Kent, 1820-1857 (Volume 23)
  - Accounts, 1848; Weaver, W. H. (Volume 24)
  - Passbook with W. H. Lewis, Grover, Govt. Street, Mobile, Alabama, 1850; U.S.S. (Volume 25)
  - Notebooks, meteorological observations, 1853; 2 vols.; Kane, Elisha Kent, 1820-1857 (Volume 26)
    With sketches
  - Medical casebook, 1856-1860; Kane, Elisha Kent, 1820-1857 (Volume 27)
  - Journal kept at Blockley Hospital, 1840-1841; Kane, Elisha Kent, 1820-1857 (Volume 28)
  - Medical lecture notes for course by Samuel Jackson, 1840-1841; Kane, Elisha Kent, 1820-1857 (Volume 29)
  - Arctic diary, 1850-1851; Kane, Elisha Kent, 1820-1857 (Volume 30)
- Series V. Graphics, ca.1840-1856; 0.25 linear feet
  Miscellaneous drawings, sketches, and photographs by and of Elisha Kent Kane, including a number depicting scenes in the arctic. Kane was an incessant doodler and agreeable artist, and the collection includes representative sketches from most of his expeditions.
  Native American Images note: Over 200 sketches, watercolors, silhouettes, maps, and engravings of Inuits of Baffin Bay drawn by Kane during the first (1850-1851) and second (1853-1855) Grinnell arctic expeditions. Primarily from the first trip, images include portraits in native attire, landscapes, dwellings, hunting tools, kayaks, and encampments. Kane’s log and notebooks are dotted throughout with sketches. Of note in the graphic series, a watercolor of an Inuit boy netting auks. Donated with his papers, Kane’s published works: The United States Grinnell expedition in search of Sir John Franklin (1853) and Arctic explorations: the second expedition…(1857) include engravings of all his original drawings. Referenced in the sketch file, the finding aid contains a detailed inventory. Also, referenced in Murphy Smith’s Historical American Sketches…in the manuscripts collections of the APS.
  - House on bay with miscellaneous doodles of fences, plants, faces on verso., n.d.; Pencil drawing; [F.Y.O.?]
  - Advance moored in fjord, n.d.; Pencil and ink drawing; Kane, E. K.
  - The Advance in ice, n.d.; Mounted ink drawing; Kane, E. K.
  - Advance schematic cross section (1 with doodles of starving men on verso), n.d.; 2 diagrams, 1 pencil and 1 pen.; Kane, E. K.
  - Angular masses and detritus in Ice Berg, Pencil drawing; Kane, E. K.
  - Boxes [schematic sketches], n.d.; Ink drawing; Kane, E. K.
  - The Brig in the winter ice, 1856 December 10; Pencil drawing; Kane, E. K.
  - Sketch of Henry Brooks, 1851 March 5; Pencil drawing; Kane, E. K.
  - Cape Melville, 1856 August 14; Watercolor; Kane, E. K.
  - Central High School, n.d.; Pencil drawing; Kane, E. K.
  - Coast of Greenland, 1850 June 22; 2 pencil drawings; Kane, E. K.
  - Coast of Greenland II, Pencil drawing; Kane, E. K.
  - Departure of the II Grinnell Expedition from New York Harbor, n.d.; Mounted pencil drawing; Kane, E. K.
  - Entering Fjord near Storae Island, Pencil drawing; Kane, E. K.
  - Faces and pulley doodles, 1850 February 18; 1 page of pen drawings; Kane, E. K.
  - First experience in the Pack, n.d.; Six small pen and ink drawings on one page; Kane, E. K.
  - Houses, n.d.; 2 pencil drawings; Kane, E. K.
  - Ice, 3 varieties, n.d.; Pencil and ink drawings; Kane, E. K.
  - Imp; shuttered window sketch and other doodles on verso, Pencil drawings; Kane, E. K.
  - Inuit man, profile, n.d.; Pencil and ink drawing; Kane, E. K.
  - Island in South Pacific [?], Pencil drawing; Kane, E. K.
  - Islets, n.d.; Pencil drawings; Kane, E. K.
  - Maps - rough drafts, n.d.; 3 items; Kane, E. K.
    - Map of Baffin Bay, n.d.
  - Miscellaneous sketches: ship on coast, a man's head, a glacier, etc., n.d.; 5 pencil drawings; Kane, E. K.
  - Models and diagrams, 3 items; Kane, E. K.
  - Musicians [doodles], [ca. 1840]; Pen and ink drawings; Kane, E. K.
  - Porto Grande, views, 5 pencil drawings on one page; Kane, E. K.
  - Silhouettes, n.d; 5 cut-outs; Kane, E. K.
  - Sailboat and steamer, Pencil drawing; Kane, E. K.
  - Sea kayak, 1850-1851; 1.0 Item(s)
    - Sea kayak, 1850-1851
  - Seal flipper, 2 views: extended and ventral portion of extended, 2 pencil drawings on 1 page; Kane, E. K.
  - Small sailboat at sea, n.d.; Pencil drawing; Kane, E. K.
  - [Nagendronoth?] Tagore, profile sketch; small map of Greece on verso., 1845 June 1; Pen and ink sketches; Kane, E. K.
  - Tomb of R. P. Kane, n.d.; Pencil drawing on verso of printed invitation from Wistar Party; Kane, E. K.
  - Venta de Fayal [Azores], n.d.; ink drawing; Kane, E. K.
  - View of Heather Field, n.d.; Pencil drawing; Kane, E. K.
  - View of Dios Polis Parva [?], n.d.; 2 pencil drawings; Kane, E. K.
  - Botanical sketches, n.d.; 2 pages of various pencil drawings; Kane, R. P.
  - Invitation to Judge and Mrs. Kane, 1851 January; 1 item; The Philadelphia Club
  - Brandywine Cottage, exterior; interior measurements on verso, Small pencil drawing.; Weaver, W. H.
  - Baffin Bay refraction, 1850-1851; 3 3/4 x 4 1/2 inches, watercolor
  - Inuit netting birds, 1850-1851; 7 x 10 1/2 inches, watercolor
  - Engraving of John Kintzing Kane., ca. 1860; 1.0 Item(s); Half length, seated, frontal view, with chin resting on hand and index finger at side of head.
  - John Kintzing Kane with sons Elisha Kent Kane and Thomas Leiper Kane., 1.0 Item(s); Group portrait of three Kane men.
  - Photograph of portrait of Elisha Kent Kane in uniform., ca. 1860; 1.0 Item(s); Half length portrait of Kane in uniform with sword, seated.
    General note
    Possibly a photograph of original portrait owned by family and sold at Kane auction in Kane, PA, 2003.
  - Sketch of Inuits in kayaks., ca. 1850; 1.0 Item(s); Sketch of kayaks and people.